[Music]
thank you
hello everyone welcome it's active live
stream number 49.2 on October 12 2022.
welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
you can find us at some of the links on
the page
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide feedback so we
can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
head over to
activeinference.org to learn more about
the kinds of projects and learning
groups you can get involved in
and we're here in stream number 49.2 in
the third video of our explorations of
the paper a worked example of the
Bayesian mechanics of classical objects
in the dot zero Jakob and Ali and I
provided some background in context then
last week in 49.1 with Dalton we all
convened and we had a great discussion
and went through a lot of that context
again and that set us up very well today
for 49.2 to be primarily going through
the paper which is very exciting so
we'll begin with just
saying hello and anything else we'd like
to add on this Wednesday
and then we will head right in so I'm
Daniel I'm a researcher in California
and I guess I'm excited to get to the
paper and understand what points are
touched upon and why and I'll pass to
jakup
hello I'm jakub I'm a student in the UK
and uh I'm excited to talk about the
different face faces of Bayesian
mechanics how they are related how they
are different uh I'll pass it to Ali
hello I'm Ali I'm an independent
researcher from Iran again I'm very
excited to be here as well last week we
had a truly amazing discussion uh with
Dalton and very much looking forward to
continue our journey through this
fascinating paper today I also have a
bunch of questions I'd like to ask
especially when we come to section 4 on
Quantum ontology and I'll pass it to
Dalton
okay uh well I'm Dalton uh I'm a
mathematician and a physicist uh
currently based at Stony Brook
University I'm also at the University's
lab
where a large part of my research
program right now is to do with the
maths and physics of the free energy
principle so I'm I'm pleased to be here
and uh thank you for for having me and
I'm happy to
um to get the conversation underway
all right well
we've looked previously at the roadmap
so let's just take one last Glimpse at
our map before we go um you know White
Knuckle on the steering wheel
maybe just one overview Dalton if you
could provide what sections are
addressed and what is the general
anatomy and physiology of the paper
uh yeah of course so as we were talking
about
um last time
uh the structure of the paper partially
reflects uh the environment that it was
written in uh in a way that is uh or has
come to characterize the free energy
principle so there's it's kind of funny
in that sense
um one of the things that was a kind of
unmet need uh was a nice paper
relatively contained that Drew together
some of the recent ideas that have been
written in the past uh six months or so
about what we've called Bayesian
mechanics and there are a few key papers
that are then uh kind of
summarized and uh put on stage
in the first uh maybe four sections and
then sections five through seven are
actually taking all of that um summary
and uh putting it into a worked example
of what uh Bayesian mechanics looks like
so we have a lot of uh rigorous
development
um to begin with and then we actually
use some of that in uh the Wild and show
okay so if you're actually to treat this
algorithmically and go and compute
something using this framework what
would it look like so in a way it's it's
kind of split roughly along mathematical
and physical lines if you'd like to
think of it that way mathematicians
really like foundational rigorous stuff
and then physicists really like to be
able to compute things and say something
about models of the physical world so in
a way it's it's trying to meet both of
those kind of metallogical needs and
that's the reason why it's structured
this way so as we go through you'll see
at some point there's a bit of a phase
transition where we go from here are all
the basic ingredients here what they
mean and how they ought to be used
to here is how we actually use them
we'll keep an eye out for that
signpost
and we'll be paying attention to the
equations as part of our Preparatory
work here it's just um those on the live
stream we'll see a subset of our Coda
page where we have all of the equations
and some awesome annotations by Ali so
we'll be able to look at the paper
and also bring in some pre-screenshotted
formalisms and we'll uh
Journey forth so
beginning with uh the introduction
what did you aim to set up in the
introductions
what did you um enter what did you want
people to have
uh prepared or their state when they
entered the introduction and leave it
and also I'm a little curious about the
acknowledgments at the end of the first
section of course yeah so if you go and
it might benefit me to have a copy of
this uh in front of me as well so give
me one moment to bring that up
um but one of the things that I wanted
to do with the introduction was really
road map exactly uh what I had just
described which is that in the last uh
couple of years and especially the last
six months
um there's been a lot written about this
thing called basic mechanics
and it is a bit of a different take on
what has traditionally been written as
the free energy principle so if you're
in the active inference literature or if
you're in the
um predictive processing literature this
is probably new to you and likewise
um if you are if you're coming from
conventional stochastic process Theory
then you're probably not familiar with
the specific technique or philosophy
underlying basic mechanics so that's
probably new to you as well so the idea
of the introduction is just to set out
okay here is basic mechanics we've
talked a lot about it in these previous
papers and
um it was probably time to
set out in detail what is it and why are
we interested in it and how do we use it
which is of course later on in the
papers the work example so in the
beginning of the introduction I just lay
out okay here is what we have called
Bayesian mechanics and here is under
what circumstances is it useful which
introduces the idea of synchronization
in the first and second paragraphs
and then in in the third paragraph uh on
the third page well the third paragraph
the first one on the third page I I
describe this idea that there hasn't
really been a kind of worked example of
this yet uh so so some of the uh Theory
uh has been worked out in previous
papers some of them mine some of them
um are uh co-authored with other people
some of them are from uh Kyle's group at
the Welcome Center at UCL
um but but in all of those
um papers there
primarily theoretical uh except for
certain uh kind of algorithmic papers
mostly out of the control theory
literature so it is worth complementing
this unified view that I try and
describe uh taking in the introduction
with an application of that unified view
if for no other reason than to uh give
it some concrete particulars uh so
that's actually a phrase from Calgary
Theory which is probably
appropriate given that category theory
is is very interested in the general and
the abstract
um
and uh and not so much in the concrete
particular
uh in fact I think that was a phrase
from uh lover who's one of the uh most
uh famous well-known category theorists
um so so it is kind of appropriate then
that part of the motivation for at least
the second half of the papers to say
okay we've done all this Theory work and
we've laid out here's precisely what
this thing basic mechanics is
um and then to to give it some uh kind
of meat to grab onto if you're someone
that likes to actually write models or
understand how to uh Shuffle symbols
around in an equation and really work
with things then uh here is something
for you that that will actually kind of
uh make things make sense to you
awesome and yes this is quite uh not an
indictment
but just reflecting the very rapid pace
of development that
much has been discussed around the role
of Bayesian mechanics as a conceptual
integrator or unifier yet
the concrete particulars remained to be
demonstrated
of course yeah and as you say it's not
an indictment because there is a place
for both and
um of course I'm biased coming from a
very uh strong mathematical background
um but I think it is it is better to go
with the more General
um more abstract uh and it's better to
build Theory rather than just deploy it
uh but it's I mean there's room for both
and and they serve different needs so
doing exclusively one or the other is uh
in my opinion and in my research
not the best way to approach a problem
uh because you need to be able to build
the techniques that solve the problems
then you also need to use them to solve
problems
um so yes not an indictment but um
uh maybe a striking observation that
there's been a lot of abstract stuff and
maybe something uh more concrete has
been missing historically in the
literature
awesome and then any thoughts on the
last paragraph
or the uh unusual positioning of the
acknowledgments paragraph
um no thoughts on the last one I think
the last one just uh draws all of those
ideas together and also says
um
one of the reasons why this approach is
interesting is it it recovers some
things of independent mathematical
interest
um which is uh what I gesture at in the
last sentence
um I put all of my uh acknowledgments at
the end of the introduction I think uh
that's just something that I developed a
quirk maybe although I think it's common
what's relatively common in mathematical
papers to put the acknowledgments
um right after the introduction
uh so I I well unusual maybe with
respect to other fields that I think put
it uh after the conclusion or after the
last section and before the references
um I I like it there I like it right
after the introduction uh because I
think it gives credit uh more visibly
um mathematical writing is kind of
unique in that often you are writing
alone but thinking together and so the
the end product the paper itself is not
always reflected and in fact is rarely
reflective of the mathematical thinking
that went into it so it's good to front
load that information it's good to say
straight away
um here are the people that I thought
about this problem with and and that's
what went into this paper is
contributions intellectual contributions
from all of these people that I had
conversations with or bounced ideas off
of
um and so so the acknowledgments is
right there in the beginning
awesome makes a lot of sense
Okay so
into section two on mechanics so for
each section I'll just kind of start up
a new page and we can bring in equations
and quotations as seen fit so let's just
begin with Section 2A classical physics
in one Dimensions why start here and
what does this section say yeah so
um section 2A is uh just a very brief
summarization of
uh what is classical mechanics uh so
this is important for two reasons really
one is it allows me to talk a little
about uh the basic building blocks that
I'm going to use in the second excuse me
second half of the paper uh so so we
start off on a point of familiarity
uh and uh if not then
you know all of that is is built up so
that uh later on the rest of the papers
uh at least referencing something that
has already been discussed
um so I just in terms of layout it makes
sense to get these preliminaries uh done
first
um the other thing is of course one of
the points of the paper or at least one
of the motivations is that uh Bayesian
mechanics is a mechanical Theory just
like any other mechanical Theory and so
to really uh make that analogy come
across it was good to investigate okay
well what are mechanical theories what
does that really mean uh so in the
context of classical mechanics uh what
do we mean by the interaction of
um stationary action principles and laws
of motion and Dynamics and all these
things that we talked about in the uh
previous episode
um what do all those look like in
classical mechanics and then the kind of
the metallurgical point of the paper in
some sense uh
well I don't know you could argue that
this is the point of the paper is to
make the analogy precise to point out
that okay all these things that live in
basic mechanics
are things that live in mechanical
theories that map onto something like
classical mechanics and that you can
prove this so really in some sense the
paper is an extended exercise in proving
that that map between something that we
know very well and something that we
maybe don't exist
um but I I would argue at least that
that's only
window dressing the real point of the
paper being
um proving stuff about base mechanics uh
and and classical mechanics is just a
useful analogy
um but I think the way it's shaped up it
kind of does both and you could argue
that uh
yeah it does one or the other
with you know one in service of the
other but but how that relationship goes
I think is maybe open to interpretation
just the way that the paper evolved uh
regardless the reason why we start with
classical physics is to put all those
pieces on the board so that later on we
can go and use them
awesome so equation one
and 1.1 just using the decimal point to
reflect on numbered formalisms that
follow a numbered formalism
um where do we get on the first page
with these equations one through two
yeah um
equation one is is starting really from
the the very Basics uh so this is the
action functional
um and in particular it's the action
functional for uh classical mechanics in
the lagrangian setting
um equation 1.1
is the result of uh finding the path of
least action or the the stationary
action uh so mathematically the way that
is done is uh by finding What's called
the Euler LaGrange equation
and and that's what this is so if you uh
if you apply the Euler LaGrange equation
to the action then
1.1 is the result
and what is interesting about that is
that gives you back uh Newton's Second
Law uh f equals m a and the reason why
is because the uh derivative of V with
respect to Q so the the gradient of a
scalar potential is a force acting on
something and the or the LaGrange
equation tells us that that F force is
equal to the mass times the time
derivative of velocity which is the
acceleration
uh so the the chain of reasoning goes
that beginning from an optimization
principle you get a law of motion and
that that kind of embodies uh a that
embodies classical mechanics in the case
when you begin from the classical action
and you get Newton's uh second law
um so the the idea is and the reason why
this is mentioned is it calls back the
reasoning uh in uh the paper on Bayesian
mechanics uh a physics oven by beliefs I
think it's the full title which uh tells
us that you know in the same way that
this exists in classical physics
um Bayesian mechanics has its own an
analogy to this so if we want to regard
this as a kind of informational physics
then we can begin with some kind of
action functional in this case the
surprisal or the free energy functional
depending on the situation
and then somehow
um
the thing that optimizes that is a law
of motion that uh describes some kind of
dynamical system uh and in the
informational or basic case that is
approximate Bayesian inference
uh and then uh once you have that law of
motion you can start plugging things in
and get dynamical theories uh based on
certain boundary conditions uh like uh
the the initial conditions or data about
what these symbols actually mean so in
the classical case you're wondering okay
what is precisely the potential that I'm
interested in what is what is the mass
what is the initial uh velocity and
position and in Bayesian mechanics you
might be interested in okay where is the
boundary for the Markov blanket
um what do my internal States mean uh so
what kinds of systems am I actually
interested in what are they doing in
France over so what is the Environmental
States they're trying to infer or at
least what do they look like to the
system
uh and and so once you do that you can
start getting from this General law of
motion this General approximate Bayesian
inference idea
um you can get actual dynamical things
uh and and models of real situations and
so the reason why
um that's kind of nice is because then
the whole last half of the paper is is
exactly well what does it mean to
produce a dynamical system out of this
law of motion if I have this very
general idea of approximate base in
inference what does it mean to actually
start writing down models of things uh
and and it is precisely the worked
example in the latter half of the paper
that gives you that back
awesome Jacob or Lee anything
or will continue to be
well not for now but okay I'll
definitely have some questions later
okay
classic section 2B or not 2B question
let's go to B
uh yes that's always good I think
um in this section uh it is basically
running through the same
um
reasoning at a very high level
uh and so this subsection to be uh is
all about okay what is space and
mechanics what do we mean by uh beta
mechanics and in a way it is kind of um
it plays on this theme of the uh paper I
just mentioned this on Bayesian
mechanics paper very nicely because this
gives us okay here are the basics of
what we're talking about
um here are all the important
ingredients and then the subsections
that follow uh are trying to build out
okay what do we mean by it's a physics
of beliefs
and then what do we mean by it's a
physics by beliefs because both of these
are kind of imprecise
um
terms and so defining these phrases in a
way that is a little more enlightening
is a nice way of uh fleshing out this
section and the contributions of the
paper so uh 2B is is about uh the basics
of basic mechanics and it just kind of
introduces the idea what do we want from
Bayesian mechanics what is it trying to
do
um how does it fit into the free energy
principle uh how does it fit into
stochastic process Theory
and so you'll see in the in this section
A lot of it is just building up the idea
that uh systems that minimize surprisal
uh as the kind of law or the
optimization principle that they follow
exhibit a kind of law of motion like
um Newton's law and its approximate base
in inference and that that follows from
this reasoning about things that
synchronize and minimize surprisal
um do approximate Bayesian inference
about the parameters of the probability
density of the system to which they're
coupled
uh so a lot of a lot of this section is
just um the very fundamentals and um we
can go through
I think equation by equation and maybe
um clarify
uh
what those things mean that might be a
good way of extracting some insight from
this so so this is exactly the uh
what I was describing you know what are
the kind of um
important ingredients what's the basic
setting of Bayesian mechanics
uh and you'll see on um
equation on uh what is it page five in
equation three
um we begin just from a stochastic
differential equation so this is some um
kind of random variable that evolves
Through Time according to uh not only a
drift so some kind of average path or
vector field on the value of the random
variable at a given time but also this
noise term at the other end of it
um so these These are modeled on what we
call controlled rough paths in
stochastic process Theory and it's uh so
you can think of this as just an
ordinary differential equation
with uh an incoming signal
and the signal is the noise it's this DW
thing is
um a what's called a beta process so
it's just white noise so you have your
uh your differential equation and then
you have some kind of random signal
coming into it uh the idea of stochastic
process theory is okay how do we make
sense of the uh kind of equation that
we're looking at here
and in particular you know there are a
couple of ways of making sense of it one
of the interesting ones uh is looking at
as this thing uh produces trajectories
so random sample paths
uh how do we understand the statistics
of those sample paths and thereby
understand something about what the
system is doing at an ensemble level
um one of the ways of doing that and
this gets into the next page and the
following equations is by understanding
okay so what is the probability of a
path
um
and and that's equation five but that
needs uh you know some Machinery we
can't just fabricate uh kind of
arbitrary probability over paths so
where do we get that from uh and that
comes from a least action principle uh
just the same as it did in classical
physics
so so that's really the uh the I think
primary point of this section is is just
to begin with OR at least one of the
primary points of this section is just
to begin with
um already some of the analogies is
taking shape because we begin from a
least action principle so s is again an
action functional just like it was in
the previous subsection
and Omega is
um a realization of noise this so it's
uh
you you can imagine it as just being one
of these uh
kind of incoming signals so what is the
what is the noise that I'm putting into
the system
and and of course that's that's where
your Randomness is coming from
so that's what we're interested in when
we're interested in probabilities over
paths is really how does a realization
of noise or a configuration of noise
affect the underlying sample path
and that comes from
this uh action so the probability is
just kind of the exponentiation of this
thing
which
um comes from stochastic process Theory
uh the same thing arises in the path
integral formulation of quantum physics
so in in that context where I've been
interested in what is the transition
probability of a particle through
space-time so that's nothing but asking
what is the probability that a particle
moves from point A to point B uh given
um a particular fixed initial Point what
is the probability that it takes a
particular path from A to B so
um path integrals are like path
probability density so at least they
produce these things
uh so the it's it's interesting and it's
not a coincidence that the same thing
shows up there that if you take the
action on paths and you just put e to
the minus s
then you get a path integral although
I've I've kind of left some details out
uh because that's a path integral for a
statistical uh field theory in uh kind
of uh what we call after Wick rotation
and so the in Quantum field Theory we
add an i it's an imaginary variable but
these things are mathematically
um transferable so it doesn't really
matter for our purposes uh in what
context we talk about them
uh so so that's that's where equation
five comes from is if we have this
action and we just do e to the minus s
then uh
what we get is a path probability
density
um and and as you've written there uh
this um again it doesn't come out of
nowhere it's uh it's consistent with
um stochastic process Theory uh so all
of the sample Paths of a stochastic
process uh if they're continuous they
live in what's called an abstract Dino
space and the probability density over
an abstract venous space is exactly this
e to the minus s thing
so so that's where that comes from and
it's uh it's nice that that kind of
falls out of basic mechanics
um very naturally
so if you begin from the reasoning that
we want an action and the least action
principle and that that tells us
something about the uh trajectories of
the system then there is a very
canonical way to get back the uh Vienna
measure
um it's not surprising in some sense but
it's nice that it's consistent with that
so uh I talk a little about okay what is
this what does this mean and how is this
equivalent to a surprisal because I
think that's important too
um and uh so the action that I talked
about previously I guess so called 4.1
um does come from
the uh
yes so 4.1 uh that s is equivalent to
the surprisal and and that comes from if
you just put a logarithm on both sides
of equation five you get log P equals uh
minus s and uh so if you put a minus on
both sides and you get minus log P
equals s
so the surprisal of a trajectory is
equivalent to this integral over time of
the uh noise squared uh so by the way I
don't know that I defined those brackets
but the brackets just means you take the
two things inside the bracket and you
multiply them by each other so so really
this is just the integral through time
of the noise squared
and that that is equivalent to the
surprisal is more interesting for our
purposes because it means the converse
also holds if you start from the point
of the abstract Venus space and you
write down the correct action then you
get uh basic mechanics back as the idea
that something that minimizes its action
in the right in the Bayesian mechanical
setting minimizes its surprisal
um so I'll let you write that down uh
and then we can carry on I think from
page seven because the rest of page six
is just uh same all of that
sure I think surprisal
may be more conventionally understood in
a statistics framework but what is
action and this is this related to me
moving my arm action or what do we mean
by action here yeah uh so in the context
of
um physics and and mechanics
um an action is a functional so it takes
a function and it gives you back a
number
um
and as a functional what it does is it
gives you a kind of a weight or a cost
associated with a trajectory so if you
write down a path through space or
through space time as a specific
function
then the action takes that function and
gives you back the cost of taking that
path and so the idea in classical
mechanics is okay the uh the cost
Associated to a path is based on how
much extra energy does it take if you if
you take that path from A to B
um and extra energy is kind of circular
in this sense it kind of presupposes the
uh least action path exists but then uh
if you'll allow that for a moment then
the idea is okay so there should be a
path that uses the least extra energy to
get from A to B uh and in doing so it
produces the least cost so finding the
least action path the path of minimum
action uh is the way the optimal way to
get from A to B and in In classical
physics Paths of least or stationary
action more generally are the only
acceptable paths
um when you start to introduce noise it
becomes a probabilistic judgment so
Paths of least surprise are the most
likely paths you have other ways to get
from A to B as well if there are like
very large fluctuations for instance
um so so in in that sense you can think
of action as kind of a loss functional
um or something analogous to it in the
machine learning world because it it is
a judgment about how good
um a path from A to B is
it's not before we go to the next
section Ali or Jakob do you want to add
anything
okay
that was page six now we're going to
page seven
yeah so then I um
go on with this story about
synchronization uh which is is
introduced here in in some greater
detail than has previously been done I
think which is one of the points of the
paper uh so I begin by saying okay let's
take two um random dynamical systems uh
which I I call eat and mu this is kind
of uh well it's not kind of it is an
abuse of types so just be aware when
you're reading this
ETA and mu are states of the random
dynamical system
but a random dynamical system is a bit
more complicated than that there's more
Machinery going on in the background
however just like we would write uh kind
of a big capital X as a random variable
so we name the uh sde after the values
of its states
we can
do the same with the random dynamical
system if we wink and Nod and and
remember that that's not quite correct
um but uh it's it's also worth pointing
out that a random dynamical system can
be identified with an sde under the
right circumstances
um and that you do so very easily uh so
this this is totally consistent with the
um previous discussion
uh and I I have a paper forthcoming that
does that in a bit more detail uh so
it's it's continuing along these lines
and saying Okay
um if we begin from the space and
mechanical story of systems that are
coupled to each other do inference
um and if they are random dynamical
systems then that inferences uh
meaningful and comes with a path of
probability density and all this
um that's in Greater detail in this
forthcoming paper
uh so so anyway that's kind of technical
remarks um but just keep in mind in that
in the first sentence there's a bit more
going on there but I'm allowed to do
that because it all works out anyway
uh and then we begin with this thing
about synchronization so you know when
you uh consider
coupled systems then those systems
synchronize so there's some relationship
between the statistics of those two
systems
uh and and that is this uh Sigma
function that is given in earlier
literature by uh
people like um Carl and people in his
group
uh
so the sigma is relating the average
internal state to the average external
States it's even called the
synchronization function in that
literature uh and in this case we
actually also want to be able to say
um not only a state at a given time but
also that the paths of the system
synchronize so taking it a little bit
more generally then has been written uh
before you know we now want to be able
to say that okay so now uh the the
trajectories of the random dynamical
systems um synchronize so how one
evolves depends on how the other evolves
which is um conceptually is is fine
um and relates all to things that have
already kind of been worked out like
active inference you know how an active
inference agent evolves Through Time
depends on how its environment evolves
through time and vice versa because
um active inference agents can act on
their environment and change it uh so
and you know Control Systems more
generally are things that fit into this
trajectory based formalism
so uh then I talk a little about
um surprisal so what does it mean that
systems that synchronize minimize their
surprisal
and there's a lot of there's a lot to
detail in uh this section there's a lot
of stuff that goes along with that
statement but ultimately it's just
saying that systems that synchronize
with each other
um almost by definition are minimizing
the magnitude of fluctuations away from
whatever is being synchronized to so
this relationship means that you are
minimizing your surprisal if surprise
was defined as deviations away from the
thing that is being synchronized to
so that I think um
again that's that's almost
um a tautology but uh
that's I think kind of the power of the
framework is you begin from this
statement that makes
um almost uh trivial conceptual sense
and then it's it gives you some kind of
actual useful model of what the internal
dynamics of some system are doing
uh and that's that's at the end of uh
page seven
great I'll ask a specific and a general
question from the chapter so first the
specific question and just let me know
which equation to look at Martin Beale
asks what is the relationship between X
of T and gamma
um gamma is a path so it's a realization
of uh x t the random variable X of T is
just another way of writing gamma
um I do it in a couple of different ways
uh just to drill down the point that uh
lots of different literature lots of
different ways of seeing this thing are
all the same so for instance gamma is
used in the literature around maximum
caliber so this maximum path entropy
um
X of T is kind of consistent with this
functional idea so regarding a path as a
function
um and then plugging it into the
functional and seeing okay what is the
surprise what's the the cost associated
with this path
um and you'll also see I think Q of T
later in the paper and that's
interesting because Q is the uh the
variable and Q of T is conventionally
used in classical physics literature
um just again as a mathematical
convention
um so anyway yes to turn to your
question gamma is just this x of T
though they're different labels for the
same object okay and Martin follows up
is this synchronization an additional
assumption to Bayesian mechanics or is
it part of the assumptions for it
and then is X of T gamma of t
um
okay so the idea of synchronization is
critical to Bayesian mechanics actually
telling you anything useful
um because the whole story about uh
coupled things do inference on each
other is something that follows from uh
this synchronization so the whole story
about approximate Bayesian inference
um follows from the coupling so
synchronization is an important
assumption
um one thing that you can do however is
to prove that things that synchronize
um are coupled and vice versa things
that coupled uh are synchronized
um and this is uh at least shown in
uh paper I have from earlier this year
called towards a geometry and Analysis
for Bayesian mechanics I I believe
that's in
um lemma's 4.2 and 4.3 and maybe theorem
4.2
um so shown that if you you know if you
write down two coupled systems then you
can get the um statistics to synchronize
that's not really it wasn't difficult to
show and it's not really surprising but
but that is something that you can show
um gamma of T I don't think I use gamma
of T in the paper
um
maybe I use gamma sub T So gamma T like
uh sort of set a offset from from the
main line
um gamma sub t uh is uh again the same
notation that's
um used elsewhere
uh
so it just means a a path at a
particular time point so it's just a
state a realization of the random
variable
um at that time
okay okay and then the more general
question before we head on was from Dave
who wrote what does using energy mean
for example is that extracting potential
energy and transferring that withdrawal
to kinetic energy or the relevant
analogues
yeah um in the context of an action
functional that's exactly what it means
uh so this transfer of potential energy
to
um energy of motion
uh which is kinetic energy
um
yeah I think uh there is a discussion of
this a kind of conceptual discussion of
this in the on Bayesian mechanics paper
um somewhere in section two I think
uh and it's it's the idea that okay when
we talk about minimizing action it's
about
you have some energy budgets your
potential energy
um and you want to know okay what is the
most efficient way of using that budget
what is the most uh what is the way that
transfers potential energy to kinetic
energy with the least accumulated uh
loss over time
um and
physically that is just following a
force gradient so if you if you try to
do extra if you try to
wiggle your way through the force
gradient you now need to invest more
potential energy but you're getting to
the same spot
so that's not necessarily what you want
to do so this is why the Euler LaGrange
equation is kind of interesting because
it tells us what we intuitively expect
is the the most efficient way of
transferring an energy budget to actual
motion is just following along a force
gradient and that's why we see things
like Newton's law that uh the
acceleration of the system is always the
force acting on it or in proportion to
it anyway because you also have this
Mass constant
awesome on to page eight equations six
seven and eight
yeah um so this is setting up the uh
the variational free energy
so we have uh in six and seven
um
we have the kind of traditional uh
factorization that that we've seen in a
lot of this literature uh which is here
is the free energy functional with the
um joint density the kind of generative
model
um and then if we take out this extra
surprisal term then we get the variation
of free energy
um in a kind of reduced form which
bounds the actual surprisal of the
internal states of the system the the
blank or the particular states of the
system the blanket and the internal
States uh so then this this um
kind of sets us up to say Okay then if
the system is synchronizing well so if
it's minimizing its surprisal and it
matches the uh mode
in the uh the first um log term then
that bound vanishes and we are putting a
bound on the surprise of internal States
and then equation eight uh just States
it again in the setting of paths and not
States
so you have these uh these functions ETA
of T mu of T is about the evolution of
the system through time
all right Jacob early anything you want
to add there
[Music]
okay
now we get to the physics of and by
beliefs we could have completed the
Constitutional Trifecta with the four
beliefs
also some very interesting connections
that Jacob and I and others have
explored with grammatical case for
example the physics of belief being the
genitive case whereas the physics by
belief might be like the instrumental
case and that might Point towards
natural and semi-natural languages to
describe beliefs but just broadly what
is happening in these sections and how
do we get towards equation nine
yeah so in this section there's just two
the the you know at the end of the
previous section um synchronization
gives you surprise minimization
um and in section c I'm I'm using the
building blocks to actually uh make that
statement so approximate Bayesian
inference is about how A System's
beliefs behave given that they need to
match some uh kind of density over uh
the environment and where match means
not necessarily equal but synchronized
to
so so this is what we mean really by
physics of beliefs uh is the um context
for Bayesian mechanics is certain kinds
of systems that are coupled to their
environment or that are coupled to
another system synchronized to that
other system
uh and as a result
um we can understand the statistics of
one system as synchronizing to the
statistics of the other system so any
kind of
um belief updating or any kind of large
deviations principles or anything that
we can use to understand the statistics
of one
are done implicitly in the context of
the statistics of the other
um
and then this so again again this is
what we mean by physics of beliefs is
suddenly we have now formulated a kind
of law of motion for the beliefs of the
system which is to do with
synchronization and the products of
Bayesian inference
um so so the idea that uh we can
understand
um sometimes literally Motion in the
sense of motion on a statistical
manifold Right movement in a space of
beliefs we can understand it as being a
response to the pressure to minimize
surprisal given whatever you are or the
system is synchronizing to that's really
the the main thrust of this section
uh and
I I talk a little about you know exactly
what does that mean
um and what is the point of
synchronization I don't think there are
a lot of equations in this section
um but but this is about it's about that
it's about okay synchronization is a
thing that we've talked about a lot
um and we've caught we've talked about
it in the context of minimizing
surprisal but um it's important to set
up the idea that uh when we talk about
basic mechanics it is partially about
the system itself but what makes it kind
of specialist it's about the beliefs of
the system and it's saying okay here is
a way of understanding coupled systems
by forgetting about the systems
themselves and going into synchronized
beliefs and understanding how to
synchronization affect the probabilities
that we assign to system States
great so that's all beliefs
and now we go to by belief oh first
Jacob
yeah um I'm just wondering
how uh how would you say that active
states are formalized within Bayesian
mechanics because I I feel like
sometimes it
um there's this kind of Duality where we
can say that systems can be described by
Bayesian mechanics and we say that they
act as if they're performing Bayesian
inference then there are also systems
which uh in this kind of conventional
sense do perform Bayesian inference
through
some active States so just one uh just
wondering how do active or even sensory
States
fit within Bayesian mechanics yeah
that's a good question
um because as you said you know
sometimes uh especially for very simple
systems this is a kind of mathematical
technique it's it's even a trick in some
sense that's not to say that it doesn't
work uh but it's it doesn't have the
kind of
epistemological sense of belief
um or or if it does you've got to do a
lot of work to make that make sense
um and I I am kind of
there's a lot of philosophical debate
about this in in the literature and I
know there's a corner of literature that
is specifically about do things actually
minimize their free energy or is it just
a useful model
um I'm kind of agnostic I think the
whole question is
basically irrelevant
um because
the the reality is whether or not it is
true in a literalist sense or is just a
model or or whatever
at the end of the day the maths works so
yes you have to be careful about
acknowledging the limitations of the
maths to describe the actual physics and
the biology but you should be being
careful about that anyway
um and and I acknowledge that maybe I'm
I'm being a bit unfair because I'm
saying the question is irrelevant and
then going on to say you do have to be
careful about the question but um the at
the end of the day it is just maths and
uh so
whether the maths is a true model of a
system or is a model of what we think
the system is doing
is kind of
a silly question
um that it being phrased that way uh and
the reason why is because the maths is
always just a model
um
I think I think something like that
point was advanced in a paper by Mel
Andrews
um where it's said that you know the fvp
is just a model of a system and whether
the model is any good or not uh is
strictly separate from whether the model
is true or not and in general models are
not true in the sense that you know no
system is actually sitting down and
calculating okay here is the root of my
free energy functional here is what
um nature says I should be doing I'm
going to go do it
um so anyway that was kind of a
digression that wasn't directly your
question uh the the reality is yes it is
a kind of a mathematical trick and the
maths works but it doesn't always tell
the satisfying conceptual story that we
want to hear
so I think um
you're right the big difference is
um to do with how active the system is
because uh systems that can actually do
actions do have a use for storing
representations
um and you know we think about uh things
like controlled systems in this sense uh
which are systems that aren't just
minimizing their surprisal as a
mathematical truism that unsurprising
systems do on surprising things but they
are systems that exist in an environment
that is trying to dissipate them
actively because they are very far from
an equilibrium point and they need to
know you know know what the environment
is doing in order to know how to respond
to it so active states do draw a pretty
clear line between
um and I should say as well
sophisticated active States because you
can think of things like the active
states of a stone they're not very
sophisticated but a stone does kind of
uh for instance irradiate heat back into
the environment so that is an action
it's just not a very interesting one but
sophisticated active States draw a
pretty clear line between
um genuine Bayesian inference and just
kind of and like applied statistics so
to speak
um and and it's something that I haven't
really thought deeply about except to
note that this is a place where there is
a distinction to be made I talk a little
about this in the geometry and Analysis
paper that I I just mentioned
um and it shows up
um quite a lot in the forthcoming paper
uh that I mentioned in the last session
um which is uh by
um Lance and myself and Carl and a few
other people and it's called path
integrals and particular kinds
um in that paper uh in I think I
mentioned in the context of an
interesting calculation to do with
moving frames of reference but but
additionally
um there's quite a lot of work uh in
that paper and one of the key
deliverables of that paper is here are a
number of different kinds of free energy
functionals which are defined by
different kinds of
um partitions so a partition that has
active states in the partition that
doesn't
um and what are the the qualitatively
different kinds of behaviors that we're
able to describe
um and and one thing one case that that
paper tries to make is that
um there are interesting systems and
non-interesting systems and there are
lifelike systems and not lifelike
systems and that they exhibit very
different behaviors when they minimize
their free energy including you know
life-like systems are able to minimize
their expected free energy so they're
not just you know it's not just a case
of Applied statistics they're actually
one presumes holding a model of the
world and making predictions about the
world and taking actions now that
minimize free energy in the future so
that's that's a bit more sophisticated
than just a tree branch shaking in the
wind because it would be kind of
surprising if it didn't you know that's
that's a law of physics it would be
surprising if the tree branch didn't
Shake in the wind but to say that the
tree branch is doing Bayesian inference
over its environment is only true in
this I guess instrumentalist sense
um I don't know if that's actually the
right word for it I think that's a word
from the philosophy literature that I'm
not qualified to use properly but it is
it is true in the instrumental sense
that that is an instrument that we can
use to describe the Dynamics of the
system it's not true in the kind of
literal cognitive sense that the tree is
now
um
forming a model and making predictions
about its current state in the state of
the environment and then maybe pan
psychist types that would disagree with
that
um but that's that's the view I take
anyway so uh this is a very interesting
question
um I hope that answered at least part of
it
Jacob
yeah um it definitely did uh I'm just
also wondering whether
um on your point where we have
sophisticated actions and not
sophisticated actions whether that could
also be a consequence of the complexity
of the environment because in the case
of just a tree branch uh being shaken by
the wind we just have one type of one
type of mechanical force that the tree
branch is synchronizing to but in a more
complex environment with living systems
uh there are many more of of maybe not
explicit forces but maybe cognitive
forces or biological forces that the
systems might need to couple to so I'm
wondering whether the formalism could
also uh
not be uh adjusted to the complexity of
just the individual entity that we're
interested in but also to the to the
complexity of the
um influences of the environment that
the system couples to
yeah I think there's definitely remit to
say that
um simpler systems uh can only infer
simple things and so they do best in
very simple environments
um more complex things
in a way and and there are arguments
that this is why structures like the
brain evolved
um actually uh I I believe I suppose
he's listening um Martin Beale has an
interesting paper about this uh and and
I forget the title but the point of the
paper is
um there's a very neat hypothesis that
the brain evolved because it's very good
as a biological structure at handling uh
what's called counterfactual information
so the brain evolved as a prediction
Generation
Um mechanism and uh so so there's
there's remit to say that you know
complexity of an individual scales with
the complexity of the environment
um because something like a human that
wants to
self-organize very far from equilibrium
suddenly there's there's a lot more to
keep track of because there's a lot more
um acting on you to keep you down so
this speak and so you not only need
complex sensory motor Loops to respond
to all that complexity but you need a
complex
processing Hub to actually deal with all
of those variables and categorize all
that information and decide okay what
are my sensory motor Loops doing in this
situation how am I actually responding
to the things that I'm observing so yeah
definitely there is an interesting story
to be told with how the complexity of
the outside
determines the complexity of the inside
and it is kind of again a very nice
um meta application of the fep Because
if you think that you know if we want to
say that things that self-organize are
things that mirror their environment
then it is precisely the claim that if
you want to be a complex thing and you
are subject to very complex
environmental forces then you need to be
a complex thing to self-organize so
and this is the kind of good regulator
type theorem that has come to
characterize discussions about the fep
so yes another interesting question
great well just to carry forth and get a
first pass and everything although of
course the door is always open for DOT
threes and Beyond
in section 2D the physics of beliefs we
have equation 9 10 11 and several more
so where do we get to by the end of
section 2D what's the key piece here
yeah so I uh in in the previous
subsection I spent a lot of time
um building up the idea that uh Bayesian
mechanics is a kind of a special way of
thinking about
Laws of Motion in the space of beliefs
so emotion on a statistical manifold
which is one really interesting thing
about it
um and and that's of mathematical
interest maybe because it's now saying
okay here is here are some kind of new
dynamical uh systems theories on
statistical manifolds
um which is is quite cool and it does
um
kind of uh I think it's that's
interesting on its own
um but if you are into physics or
biology
um that's not quite enough
the the nice thing is uh that there is
this idea that okay it's not only about
um Laws of Motion in information
geometry but it's about uh mapping a
system which has some kind of physics in
the real world into a ideally simpler
physics in uh statistical manifold so uh
in in virtue of talking about
synchronization as a law of motion uh
for beliefs we are now saying okay we
don't need to talk about the material
physics underlying the synchronization
we can go into this space of beliefs and
we can say Okay synchronization tells me
that
um the system's beliefs are changing
this way and that reflects a physical
change of this nature so it's it's an
equivalent way of talking about real
physics
so we have a physics of beliefs and that
this Maps back and forth between a real
physics
uh so we should then be able to uh make
inferences about real systems using
basic mechanical laws
and this is what is meant by a physics
by beliefs is if we invert the story and
say okay now I want to know
um what is this what is a proxy with
Bayesian inference saying about the uh
mode of the system about the parameters
that are doing
um approximate base and inference
uh and and you can do that you can make
inferences about the system itself
um and if your inferences are good
then you you learn something about the
system uh so that's very general and
that's also subject to surpriseal
minimization so if you are unsurprised
then you have a good model of the system
so so now
the whole story applies to itself in
some sense if you minimize surprisal
about your beliefs about a system
minimizing surprisal then you can get a
model of how that system is
self-organizing
um and and you hope that the loop kind
of closes
uh so so this is I think
um quite an important Point
um it's the subject of a duality
relationship that I um gesture at and
write a lot about in uh the geometry and
Analysis paper it also shows up in a
paper called the map territory fallacy
fallacy
um it has fallacy twice in the title uh
and that's that's
um by uh myself Maxwell ramstead and
Carl friston
uh and it investigates the idea that you
can you can actually turn the story on
its head and make a model of a system
making a model of its environment
and that that's insightful for various
reasons
the the interesting thing about that is
um it now gives you a physics by beliefs
in the sense that now my
um my description of what the system is
doing uh so my description of the
material physics is inferential it's
based on my beliefs about what the
system
um is synchronizing to and how well is
it minimizing surprisal and it's also
based on you know how good my model is
so it's based on whether I can minimize
my own surprisal and make good
inferences about the system
um and uh this calls back to
um the principle of constrained maximum
entropy because what that's saying is my
model of the system is an inference of
the system subject to the constraint
that
the um model of the system reproduces
surprisal minimization so any model that
I have of the system must say that the
model is itself or that the system is
itself holding a model of its
environment and is minimizing surprisal
um so that's where the constraint comes
from it's that you know this is
something that we know our priori so
it's something that we should
incorporate into our model of the system
um this surprisal minimization uh and
that just working out the maths of that
is um all of these equations so it's
showing that if you put a constraint
that your model of the system includes
um surprise or minimization then you get
back exactly approximate Bayesian
inference so there's this other route to
Bayesian mechanics that just says okay
if we begin from and and in reality and
the point I try and make is that it's
not actually a different route to
Bayesian mechanics because all this is
saying is if my model of the system
begins from the point of view that
systems that synchronize minimize their
surprisal then I get back the
minimization of free energy and
surprisal in the content text of the
system
so
kind of nuanced I think that there's a
lot of moving pieces But ultimately
that's all that means when we say
physics by beliefs is it's the
application of the constrained maximum
entry principle to create a model of a
system which is minimizing its surprisal
and and what's interesting is that that
model itself is subject to
the laws of basic mechanics because it
is a probabilistic belief so it's like
saying I'm sitting in the environment
and I'm synchronizing to the system
which is synchronizing to me
and if I make a good model of that
system I incorporate the knowledge that
it is doing approximate base and
inference that shapes my own approximate
Bayesian inference about the system this
is there's this uh the Symmetry to the
problem that falls out of very first
principles considerations
excellent
on to section three a general equation
for Bayesian classical mechanics
so it'll be helpful for you to situate
where it begins and then how we approach
equation 15.
yeah
um so this section is uh kind of taking
those building blocks okay so we have a
way of
um modeling systems that model their
environment and it's this kind of dual
surprisal minimization problem so how do
we actually write that as a problem
um that we can solve how do we do
computations with this thing in the
context of classical physics especially
um and also this analogy that we talked
about previously
um does that go through
uh to this case so
uh you can build up this idea you can
build up the idea of a classical
physical system that couples to its
environment
um and it is uh in this case a force
that acts to separate the thing from its
environment
um so again there's a bit of a an abuse
of types in the sense that we would
usually consider a sensory State
experiencing or measuring that Force
um but we so instead I just plug in the
force itself
um under the assumption that it's not a
noisy sensor maybe
and that proves to be again
um not a taxing assumption uh because it
tells us the same story uh at the end uh
you can you can you know deduce
everything that you need to
um so you can set up a synchronization
function in that case
um and it just tells the system uh what
the environment is probably like given
the force acting on the system uh and
and already you have the ingredients for
um approximate Bayesian inference
because you have a conditional
Independence so you know the system
doesn't need to know what the
environment is like if it knows the
force acting on it so you can argue that
there is a conditional Independence
there or at least a sparse coupling
um
and you have an inference problem
because the system does need to know
what to do given the force acting on it
so it does need to know what is the
environment like given that force and it
can only do what it needs to do if it is
uh minimizing surprisal so all the
ingredients are there and you can also
talk about the fact that the classical
action
is the basic mechanical action in the
limit of no uncertainty so you do get
surprisal minimization as equivalent to
uh the classical action minimization and
and that's ultimately the chain of
reasoning that gets us down to equation
15 is that the uh
that path that minimizes the classical
action
is the mode so it is the most likely
path so the path of least surprisal so
you can you can structure classical
mechanics as a least surprisal uh
problem
and that that gets us down to equation
15.
excellent
while I bring 15 in Ali or any thoughts
so maybe could you read equation 15
um with the variables and or the natural
language
um semantics
yeah um I'm I'm a big fan of that I
think that's a a useful way of breaking
things down is um explaining the objects
being involved and uh there are people
that uh that really um take that
philosophy to the extreme
um to the extent that I've seen talks
where you're not allowed the chair of
the session says okay you're not allowed
to just tell me the name of the thing
you need to explain to me what the thing
is and what it's doing
um isn't that a case of the chair doing
inference on you yeah well maybe uh I in
fact probably it is yeah how do I best
fit this into my world model well tell
me in terms that I understand yeah
explain it to me that's really what it
is
um yeah so so here um we have the path
probability density so it's it's the
probability of a a classical position Q
at a time t
um which is a joint density in this case
it equals the um
exponential of the minus of the action
that we saw in the basics of Bayesian
mechanics section
so it is the normal path probability
density
um
and the only question is okay what is s
uh
excuse me so we we've plugged in
something interesting for us it's the
integral over time
of the
uh deviation
of the classical path Q
from the path of least action where the
path of least action is defined as the
double integral of the force divided by
the mass so the double integral of an
acceleration
which is just a position
so
um given that we know the initial
conditions what is in the uh the
vertical bars so what is being squared
is just the deviation of Q the classical
path
from the expected path or the path of uh
least action
excuse me so so this is precisely the
classical action
um
in the sense that it it gives you back
the path of least classical action gives
you back the path that follows Newton's
Laws
excellent
so
to uh bring it closer one level what
variable might we be talking about like
what kind of data set or variable myqb
in uh In classical physics we're mostly
interested in uh spatial positions
or at least
um generalized coordinates describing
those spatial positions
but uh more generally we could talk
about a lot of things Q could be really
anything
um one of the nice things about uh
random dynamical systems and random
variables is there is a great generality
in what that state could represent so in
in general it's just a label for
something here in In classical physics
yeah we are interested in uh positions
uh spatial positions
okay so it could be
um how excited I am about a song or my
belief about the temperature or what
this person's next sentiment is going to
be yeah yeah all right
anything else on three or it'll be great
to move to four
no I think that's that's really the
story about three awesome well four Ali
would you like to set up or introduce
how you see section four and what you
wanted to ask
uh well yeah
um actually if you permit I wanted to
make a somewhat a lengthy comment here
uh if I may not too long I promise uh
we're gonna need a 0.3 I think I'm
following that uh with a question
um you see as we know there are numerous
approaches proposed for driving
um classical properties from
um Quantum matter so to speak but I
wanted to mention uh too among which uh
which to my mind are particularly
congress with Bayesian mechanics uh View
and Quantum quantum physics uh I'm not
sure if you're familiar with causal
fermion systems uh approach developed by
Felix Finster and Edwards because it's
not a particularly well-known Theory but
in any case it's basically another
variation a variational approach for
explaining the emergence of a strong
structured space time with all of its
Associated phenomenological properties
such as the flow of time the chain of
causal events and so on
from an optimal configuration of
self-organizing quantum wave functions
but instead of defining the action
functional as the surpriseal to be
minimized in order to achieve the
optimal inference as we saw in Bayesian
mechanics they Define the causal action
as the action functional minimizing
which leads to the optimal configuration
of wave functions which in turn results
in the structured space-time properties
and the other approach I wanted to
mention is uh Quantum Darwinism proposed
by uh wojak zurek inspired by the
principle of natural selection which
attempts to explain uh how the most
stable pointer states which attempt
are favored among the many possible
Quantum States and thereby resulting in
the classicality of our everyday
observations actually this approach is
also alluded to uh fields at all's paper
free energy principle for General
Quantum systems I guess so
juicy Bayesian mechanics does ultimately
a unifying all these different
approaches somehow into an M Theory like
integrated Theory because in your recent
paper on the map of territory fallacy
fallacy which you mentioned uh fep has
already shown to be the ideal modeling
tool for generic systems in statistical
physics so can this statement be
potentially extended to Encompass all
the other physical systems as well
yeah uh that's a good question
um I'm not familiar with this uh causal
uh fermion systems work
um although it sounds uh like it fits
into
um a kind of spirit of question uh that
exists in condensed matter Theory asking
about okay how do things
um emerge that have a given structure uh
from things that don't have structure
and especially the idea the word causal
um seems to interesting because a lot of
condensed other people are very
interested in information Theory very
recently
um
but anyway uh yeah so so there is there
is similar work in condensed matter
um by people like um uh Michael Levin
who's not the Mike Levin that does uh
developmental biology at Tufts it's
which is kind of interesting uh it's a
different Michael Levin
um and uh and Levin and someone called
when have developed uh things like um
string net condensation which is uh all
about
um how do uh
well I guess at a high level it's it's
about how does uh
structure arise from the application of
constraints to uh
I guess you might call them
self-organization uh in you might call
them self-organizing field theories
um although that's not the language that
Levin and when use and I think that's
kind of
um
telling the wrong story maybe but but
there's something there definitely
something to be generalized
um and likewise for Quantum Darwinism
there is this idea that you know uh
the things that we measure as the most
certain
um or the classical States
arise from a
spatial interaction component so things
that couple to other things
um have well-defined measurements so you
know pointer States
um
because of this localized interaction
I apologize it's so you know this is as
a as a resolution of um I think the
decoherence problem
um this is one interpretation and and it
just remains to kind of make that more
mathematically rigorous and you know
people like Sean Carroll have written
about this at length
um so in in both cases there is kind of
a
uh
yeah an intersection of ideas
um and they they both seem very basic
mechanical I think one of the nice
things about basic mechanics is it's
very general it's it's just a story
about how constraints and surpriseal
minimization and statistics interact to
get you a model of a physical system
um so
yeah in principle that is very general
and you start to add you know extra
constraints and things um like the
Markov blanket and
um and whatnot but
there is probably remit to uh generalize
this even further to uh something that
is purely about how do uh paths that
synchronize behave probabilistically and
and that is uh very general and that
probably applies to more than just uh
conventional classical statistical
physics but
um maybe other aspects of quantum
mechanics and condensed matter Theory
and and so forth
three thank you
well in our last 30 minutes of the
dot two with of course the Dot 3 on
demand let's get to those worked
examples and we will look forward to a
thousand notebooks blooming with people
simulating and making interactable
visualizations and extending some of
these examples it'll be great though to
hear what are the real world situations
that you are applying Bayesian mechanics
to and then what do each of these
equations do on the path towards
application each of these settings so
previously we discussed the three phases
of phasing mechanics so could you just
review the three phases of Bayesian
mechanics in light of where we're gonna
go in the coming applications
uh yeah of course so the uh the kind of
pyramid that you see here is at the
bottom layer is all of these uh
I guess boundary conditions specific
applications of the fep where the uh
boundary condition that we're interested
in is whether
um
the the mode being matched whether the
thing that we're synchronizing to is a
state
uh and then
you have States and paths that's the
first split and within States you're
also interested in okay is that state in
motion or is that state fixed uh and
this corresponds really nicely to a
story in classical mechanics about
forces in equilibrium uh forces being
applied and uh kind of continuous forces
uh which the the examples I used are an
object at rest
um an object that is moving to a point
at which it would rest and an object in
constant motion like something in orbit
um so and specifically for the middle
one I think I use a ball thrown in the
air and So eventually it comes back down
to earth and rests on the ground
uh and and then the celestial body a
planet in orbit is your path tracking uh
yeah
okay so we have the analogy very clear
and we can say rigorously supported the
left side we're talking about
synchronization to States like parameter
values that are instantaneous whereas
the right branch is the density over
path so the synchronizations to a path
on the left side we have fixed and
dynamic mode mode
the mode mode fallacy fallacy and that
is matching to a ball at rest and a ball
thrown in the air on a parabola that
will come to rest and the satellite
motion is the infinite chasing now
we're talking about cognitive systems
so what are the cognitive analogs or the
real world cognitive settings where
we're talking about some cognitive
entity like a computer or a person or an
ant colony rather than perhaps a ball on
a hill mm-hmm yeah so this is a good
question
um I think in the path tracking case at
least it's pretty obvious that this is
um active inference this is a very
general blueprint for what it means to
be in a dynamic environment and to
constantly be synchronizing to an
environment that's changing and that uh
maybe you yourself are changing
um and that's maybe something that's
worth commenting on
um it's it's only this last case that is
the kind of stuff that we're interested
in uh in terms of worked examples when
it comes to genuinely cognitive systems
and it's this last case that we know the
most about in terms of work examples uh
so it's the case that you know hasn't
been really worked out
um in terms of rigorous maths although
uh that's in the last six months or so
that's what's been um being done uh not
only with this paper but also with the
path integrals paper that's about to
come out and the free energy principle
made simpler but not too simple
um and also uh Lance and Carl and Greg
have a paper called geometric sampling
methods in optimization and adaptive
agents where this is also talked about
um so so in a way this is the case that
we know the most about and it's the case
that works the best it's the case that
actually explains the kinds of stuff
that we want to explain
um but the the rigorous maths hasn't
been done in that case
um the the simpler density Dynamics
um formalism is uh much less useful
and uh and to some extent suffers from
its own problems in terms of edge cases
and uh maybe mathematical confusions
um
so so there is some cleaning still to do
with the density of the state's
formalism but but again ironically
that's that's the formalism that we care
the least about and and what we're most
interested in is making the uh path
tracking
um make more sense and and making it
more complicated and generalizing even
past it to explain things that
synchronize two paths in a more complex
way
um so so the path tracking is about uh
these kinds of things and and one way to
think about them is in terms of expected
free energy so you know not only
um minimizing my three energy right now
but minimizing my expected free energy
along the path
um
that's that's one way of thinking about
it and and another way of thinking about
it is minimizing the surprise or other
path
um
so you know that's mathematically that
works nicely but it kind of it gives you
a bit of a different story and and the
expected free energy uh is a is nicer in
the context of cognitive agents because
it gives you this idea of prediction and
action back
um the density Over States formalism is
much simpler
uh and it doesn't apply
um you know much doesn't apply very
strongly to very complex agents you can
think of it as an instantaneous
approximation
um to the path tracking and so in that
sense there are things that uh are
cognitive and do
um fixed mode tracking
uh or what we call mode matching
but if you think about it that is again
an instantaneous approximation to uh the
the path tracking setup so if you think
about
um something like URI
um where usually not matching a mode
because that means we are staying
completely still and our environment is
staying completely still
um and that happens mostly at death
which is uh it is something that we can
talk about we can talk about
um a system at total rest
uh but even then the analogy breaks
because the environment still isn't at
rest only on very brief time scales can
we approximate it as being at rest and
it's also not the story that we're
looking for about cognitive agents
um so the the fixed mode and the dynamic
mode are mathematically interesting but
I think when it comes to the biology and
to some extent even the physics they're
not very interesting
people
very interesting
so maybe as we scan through these
equations just what are each equation
doing within the example so we're in
terminal mode matching section 6A and we
see equation
primarily 17.
yeah so equation 17 is just giving you
um
so I think we skipped section five which
is the mode matching uh so so maybe I do
want to just quickly mention that when
you have forces at equilibrium and you
have an initial condition of zero
um this is in equation 16
um then the path of least action is not
a path at all it's a stationary object
it's an object at rest and so you can do
this very easily you'll see I write Q
minus 0 squared equals zero so this
surprisal
um that is the surprise right you're not
integrating through time because you're
only at a one time Point
um so the integral goes away and the
double integral of the force over time
is just the it's just zero because the
forces are at equilibrium so the
surprisal is minimized when Q equals
zero when there is no motion and the
system is at the mode in this case you
can imagine Q
as a generalized position correspond to
the height above the ground so when Q is
on the ground not moving at that time
Point
um you are minimizing your surprising
and that's that's what we call mode
matching and again you see this is a
very simple setting because nothing has
had literally nothing is happening and
that's not really fit for describing
cognitive agents but it is a good
um simple case just to make sure that
all the maths works in the simple case
yep I'm imagining this to be our belief
about the room is that it's 37c and the
thermometer is giving us 37 37 37 so the
most instantaneously is not being
updated and that's kind of like a
balloon is being inflated and it's
pressure matching or the ball is on the
ground so the forces are canceling out
on the statistical distributions the
Bayesian surprise is zero the prior and
the posterior are the same we're in
nostatic possible people situation
yeah exactly there are no um if you want
to imagine again this physics of belief
setting uh there is there are no forces
acting on me between observations there
are no probabilistic forces changing my
beliefs about the the system so the mode
is stationary I'm always matching the
same mode so nothing's happening no
movement on the statistical manifold
um and therefore we get mode matching
it's a very trivial case
now we introduce some forces into the
picture with mode tracking yeah so so
mode tracking is a little bit more
complicated
um because you have uh an actual
inference you're interested in where
something is and also how to get to it
uh and and there's kind of an open
question in um somewhere in this section
which is about or maybe in the following
section which asks
um is a least surprising path to a uh
Target mode also a instance of mode
tracking right and I actually I don't
know that that's something that is open
for me I think we'll encounter it
somewhere
um
yeah I don't know well we will stumble
into it anyway
um but anyway it's the idea of okay so
we want to do inference about where is a
mode that I'm not at and how do I get
there
uh in this case the example is of a ball
being thrown through the air so again
thinking of Q as a generalized position
corresponding to the height above the
ground uh I start at some initial
condition above the ground and uh
gravity is the force acting on me
telling me
um the mode that you want to be at is at
rest on the ground so in some sense you
can read this you can read
a ball being thrown through the air and
then falling to the ground as doing
inference about what gravity tells it to
do
um
and if you if you write this out you
have there is an equation of motion
which is a path of least action and it's
just this parabolic path to the ground
and if you plug that in and you minimize
the surprisal then you get a system
um kind of goes like that and and what's
more you can write this as a gradient
Ascent on surprisal
um so it's uh well gradient Ascent on
the probability density a gradient
descent on the uh surprisal so it is
literally a minimization problem because
you can get back the equation of motion
from a gradient descent on the surprisal
and that is I think we will call it 17.2
so it's the uh the third equation in
this section
um yes that's the one
uh right after the um the first labeled
one which is 17. so so this is uh this
gradient descent this minimization
problem gets you exactly the uh equation
of motion that you want so you can prove
that
um surprisal minimization tells you
something interesting about uh this case
of mode tracking
cool I'm imagining a cognitive entity a
physicist a Bayesian mechanic
modeling in their perception implicitly
or in their notebook explicitly the path
of a ball
and the uh cleanest situation would be
if their factorization and understanding
of the sparsity of the territory if
their map resembles it but no matter
yeah even if it does it still is a
different thing and will be treated
under the Bayesian mechanics as it being
by and about beliefs rather than by and
about Mass
yeah that's definitely one way of
thinking about it
um we talked a little uh last time about
um what it looks like to collaborate and
to converge on a belief and it's a
little bit like that if we assume
there's no uncertainty about where
everyone is headed and you just want to
figure out how to get there
um so if you're like a bunch of people
collaborating on an idea and you know
where at a and and I know what B is then
um this this says that the best way to
get to B from a is just to minimize your
surprisal that's the path of least
action from A to B and in this case that
means that it is precisely the most
likely path that is the path of uh the
classical object from A to B well very
interesting since sometimes it seems
like we're discussing in a value and
preference aligned setting how to do
something policies as inference whereas
there's also a discussion of where to go
and all of these other pieces
we'll just touch on each piece as
lightly as possible in a few minutes so
we can have a closing round
in b
6B
we have tracking of mode infinite mode
tracking yeah this is the kind of um
precursor to the idea of uh path
tracking which is saying okay if that
mode is constantly in motion what does
that look like and you can do the same
thing if you write out the equation of
surprisal minimization you can get the
idea of continuous motion as well
um but it's slightly more complicated
and it is slightly less conceptually
satisfying uh because it's not
surprisingly minimization it's
um sort of Surfing along level sets of
the probability so it's the probability
isn't minimized and uh and or the
surprisal isn't minimized the
probability isn't maximized so you're
not choosing the most likely
um path
uh which is one of the reasons why I
then go on to talk about path tracking
in the next section is to say you know
okay so we tried to do this thing with a
continuously moving uh mode and it kind
of worked but not really so what if we
said something about minimizing the
surprisal of paths
um you know so instead of continuous
mode tracking what if we just talked
about continuous motion tracking a path
um do these things coincide do they tell
the same story and and this is where
um the initial stuff in the basics of
basic mechanics section comes into play
because now we're talking about path
probabilities and minimizing action
functionals and at the end of the story
um you say Okay so the whole thing does
go through you can talk about selecting
the path of minimum surprisal and in
this case it is following along in a
satellite orbit based on the continuous
forces that are being applied to you so
at every turn you have a kind of
circular Force you have not only a
tangential Force outwards but also a
centripetal force inwards and if you
write this down appropriately you can
get the equation for a circular orbit
um and and so that's what this is doing
is saying okay if you have this
continuous force acting on you then can
you match a path of least surprisal and
you can
excellent and
just one last note on the first idea of
G Theory before we take a breath in our
closing round
yeah so this is kind of a complicated
section uh the the point of this section
is ultimately to say that uh two things
really
um one is that uh the case for classical
physics is a nice playground but it's
it's kind of a simple one and and the
aspirations of basic mechanics are to
talk about
um non-equilibrium complex
self-organizing systems so can we pull
something more interesting out of the
maths and it's also to make the case
that the path-based formalism is the
right thing to look at when we want to
pull something interesting out of the
maths
um and so uh so the answer to the first
question is yes and implicitly that uh
supports the the second name uh because
it says okay not only you know can we
actually get a description of
um in this case uh Chaos versus uh
integrability or or um or goddessity
versus non-organicity but also that it
comes out of the path-based formalism
very naturally and and in a way basic
mechanics is a little bit special in
this sense because the idea of a path
integral approach to classical physics
comes out of Base in mechanics very
naturally and the results in this
setting come from that path integral
approach so uh it it implicitly has this
kind of third aim that because of this
path-based formalism in basic mechanics
uh is what did the job that basic
mechanics is the thing that we maybe
want to look at in more complex systems
so so that's the the aim of this section
what this section does is it just writes
down the path integral for a system in
classical physics given that it does
phase in inference as per basic
mechanics so approximate phase of
inference if you'd like so if if you
write down a system in classical physics
doing some kind of synchronization
you you get a path integral with a
particular kind of form
uh and then
you can transform this a couple of
different ways I I do detail the
derivation there
um but they're all very standard
Transformations and you get out of this
uh something called a supersymmetry
uh now the idea of supersymmetry goes
back to uh I think the 70s is an
observation that in uh certain uh
Quantum field theories you get asymmetry
that relates different kinds of
particles
so what that means is if I write down a
Quantum field Theory with
um two different kinds of particles and
and in general they are fermions or
bosons but it doesn't actually quite
matter what
um
at least you can get specific kinds of
fermions and bosons so the story doesn't
have to be totally General
then sometimes you can exchange the
different kinds of particles and you get
the same Theory so you can freely swap
them and nothing about the physics
changes this is called a supersymmetry
it's not a usual symmetry
um in the sense that you know when we
think about symmetries we think of
geometric things that relate say two
different sides of a shape so it is a
symmetry in that it relates to different
things in such a way that nothing
changes but it's a super symmetry
because it's about particles not not
shapes say
um
the the interesting thing is uh
supersymmetry breaking
um always leads to mathematically
interesting observations and physically
interesting observations
uh so if we have access to a
supersymmetry
then the the thought is immediately okay
um what can I say with this I should
keep an eye out for something
interesting happening when this
supersymmetry breaks
and in this context the supersymmetry
breaking is about having two or more
different constants of motion
um and what that means is the system is
non-ergotic uh so ergotic systems have
one constant of motion it's just the um
energy or the hamiltonian that you'd put
into the probability measure uh
but in in non-argotic systems in
integrable systems you have multiple
constants of motion so it's not just the
energy but it's it's some other thing
um you don't know what necessarily but
but you have additional variables
uh and what's interesting about that is
then we can make the observation that
supersymmetry is about uh or is
analogous to chaos
because
um ergotic motion is chaotic it's about
things that mix and things that fill
their state space
um in sometimes unpredictable ways
whereas integrability
um non-organicity
uh is about systems that are very
predictable you you just integrate them
and you say where it will be in a future
time
so after all this derivation and
conceptual work what we end up with is a
way of saying data mechanics has an
accounting mechanism for
um chaos and not chaos
uh and and that's where I leave off I
say so so this is something interesting
that we can do with Bayesian mechanics
and it comes out of the path into a
formulation very naturally
um and and this is a very trivial case
of just classical physical systems what
can we get when we just start to
describe the complex cases of more
interesting systems like biological
physics or self-organizing uh field
theories or you know things of this
nature and that's the end of the paper
well
like paper like stream
as they say
so let us spend our last several minutes
with Ali and Jacob
any just closing thoughts or questions
or directions that you want to continue
on
well uh it was an amazingly Illuminating
Learning Journey so I wanted to thank
again Daniel Jacob and Ander for
organizing the discussion discussion
sessions leading to these live streams
and especially Dalton for his time and
uh for sharing His Brilliant insights
and expertise with us and uh on a more
personal note
uh Dalton your work has rekindled my
long forgotten the passion for
theoretical physics and I know I'll
certainly continue to explore this
fascinating area Bayesian mechanics a
lot more so uh I'm truly grateful for
that
uh
yes that's it from me and I'll pass it
to yaakov
yeah um also thanks to everyone uh
Daniel Ali under uh who participated in
the discussions I think uh
your input Ali on the
um different equations
uh was really invaluable and of course
thank you Dalton for uh firstly writing
the paper and then uh spending the time
with us uh going through it
um I'm really looking forward to future
work I
would have uh
many other other questions about how
Bayesian mechanics is related to other
areas of physics such as uh relativistic
mechanics or or
um kind of known uh the non-classical
results within quantum mechanics which
we touched on last time uh and then the
actual applications to computational
models as well uh
I think uh so I'm looking forward to
exploring these more and
uh yeah
awesome
Dalton what do you think are some of the
best ways for someone to catch up to the
frontier of Bayesian mechanics learning
and application
um yeah well first let me say
um it's been a pleasure I've really
enjoyed uh the discussions and um you
guys came in very well prepared so uh
that made it uh even richer
um so thank you for all your hard work
and thank you for having me
um I think uh basic mechanics is
um becoming uh very a very technical
side of the free energy principle
um and I think that speaks to how
ecumenical
um the fep has been and how
interdisciplinary it has been because
people come to it from many different
backgrounds including mathematics and
physics like me but also computer
science and machine learning and also
neurobiology and also philosophy
um so there's there's something in it
for everyone uh and and if you are
interested in this
um kind of more technical side
um
one thing you um you one thing you can
do and to some extent just have to do is
read
um there is a lot of literature being
published at a very fast pace in the in
the last few months uh so it can seem
like a lot to um wrap one's head around
uh but I think one thing that I have
started to be better about
um and certainly my co-authors have been
uh good about is Road mapping things so
it's it's easier and easier I think to
get a handle on
um what all is being said and how it
relates to other things being said
papers like this are a good example of
things that draw everything together
really nicely I think anyway
um but uh I don't know if I can say that
but I will anyway
um and there are other papers and uh
things that kind of break things down
and explain things in a more accessible
way than the highly mathematical highly
technical work that's also being
published
I I write uh blog posts summarizing some
of my papers sometimes so if you're
interested in those you can find them on
my website
um
also on my website I have a kind of
Bayesian mechanical bibliography where I
organize all of the recent papers in
this area and what their contributions
are that's not on my blog that's under a
page on my website called research but
nonetheless you know that's that's
something that you can look at as well
and I think everyone involved is also
fairly accessible via email I think in
my experience that's been the case
anyway I'm always available
at my email Carl is a very generous
person with his time
and people like Maxwell and Lance and
Thomas
Connor you know all the people that have
been involved are in my experience
um
people who are willing to uh take and
answer questions
um so that's that's also something to do
you know if you're reading something and
it just doesn't make sense
um
you know do get in touch with someone
and my experience uh people will be very
charitable uh in terms of um taking and
and answering uh those questions but
yeah um and there's of course the
the the one thing that is is tough is is
kind of building up the background
um for these but I think uh like
anything
um it is something that you can develop
on the Fly
um so to speak so as long as something
makes sense to you at uh some level uh
and maybe you're not an expert on the
topic uh maybe it only makes sense in
isolation and then you don't have the
the whole
um picture in your head I think in
general that's all right
um so yeah maybe uh it's it's not a very
uh satisfying answer but but at least
part of the answer to your question is
uh we'll just start reading
um and if you do get stuck then uh
people in this area uh are pretty nice
people so uh don't hesitate to contact
one of them uh if you do get stuck or if
you want to bounce ideas around
well as stated it's been an amazing
series and I know it's not the end of 49
there are decimals to come so Dalton
thanks again jakapali under thanks for
all the amazing work
till the next gradient
okay thank you yeah I'm looking forward
to um whatever comes next